so this is a question on
Detachment can't the much emphasized
teaching of
Detachment in Buddhism from sensory
Pleasures sensuality should we say
diminish one's capacity to engage fully
with life if one ceases to find Value in
sensory in sense experiences couldn't
this not lead to a lack of motivation or
emotional or lack of emotional witness
and simply
depression if you're
not if you don't have any passion
anymore well then you got what
depression well not quite
though the um depression is the lack of
motivation but not the lack of
passion that's why you
suffer because you're trying to very
passionately resist the mental state of
depression that you find unpleasant
you're not you're not not unmoved by a
depressed mind you're very actively
averse towards it so you're very
passionate yes so the depressed person
is very passionate it is still
passionate yeah because that's why
depression hurts if they were not
passionate well depression wouldn't hurt
which means they wouldn't be
depressed so lack of
motivation is one thing lack of passion
is another
thing there lack of
motivation when you've succeeded or
exactly there can be all sorts of
reasons why you lack
motivation yeah oversaturation can be
one um depression choosing the path of
less resistance it then leads to to the
depression and like inability to make to
engage with any effort becomes like like
Monumental task even even the small
small efforts become
unbearable like it's all just through
choosing passionately path of less
resistance for whatever reason maybe you
were Justified maybe you were not but
that course of action takes you in that
direction or yes you could lose
motivation because you're truly
dispassionate and you you you would have
fully understood sensation and the
benefits of Detachment and freedom that
comes from it but you were nowhere near
passionate and nowhere near depressed
and certainly nowhere near choosing the
path of less resistance because you're
not going to get to a state of
dispassion thought in Buddhism if you
keep choosing the path of less
resistance internally it's quite the
opposite it's going against the stream
so it's always choosing the part of
higher resistance so whatever your mind
doesn't want to do that's what you need
to look
into oh keeping the precepts no start
justifying rationalizing it it's like
hold on
why so that's that's how you train the
mind that's how you develop that whole
Noble athal Path and all the aspects
that the Buddha talked about that then
do result in factual
dispassion but even even say in your
ordinary life you are dispassionate
towards some things you're not
passionate towards everything all the
time it's just you don't recognize the
value of that dispassion you still
measure everything through the lens of
passion hence then the issue of
depression and so on because the passion
is there but there's no more effort or
zeal to to fulfill
it to provide for it so then it's just
the unfulfilled
pain and so for the ordinary person that
idea of being detached and not
emotionally charged is
just scary life yeah exactly well that
yeah that's a that's a probably accurate
observation because yeah it wouldn't be
the life the way you know
it so that's again that's why people no
no no nobody will accidentally commit to
this or on account of truly correctly
commit to this practice because it leads
you against pretty much all your
familiarity and that's not pleasant only
those who recognize the problem with
life the problem with passion the
problem with desires the Deep problem
that really it's not optional whether you
really it's not optional whether you
should solve it or not then those people
could Master enough uh determination and
Master enough uh determination and
inspiration to keep swimming against the
stream they would understand that the
the greatest pleasure and in release
from burden and freedom comes from the
true Detachment but see that Detachment needs
Detachment but see that Detachment needs
to be cultivated on the level of your
lifestyle and all those choices that we
talk about of renunciation and so on
it's not just like a mental
exercise that having
willingly engaged with acts desires
Cravings intentions that lead to more
attachment that revolve around existing
attachment having not been keeping those
choices in check then just on top of it
practice Detachment in regard to things
that you are still very much connected
to that's just wishful thinking that's
just fantasy world it's people basically
that don't go against the
stream believe that they are practicing
against the stream just to kind of
appease the guilt of still flowing with
the Stream